Assesment Task:-

1.Write a blog on Difference between HTTP1.1 vs HTTP2 ?

HTTP (Hypertext Transfer Protocol) is the backbone of communication over the World Wide Web. 

1.Protocol Multiplexing:
			HTTP/1.1: In HTTP/1.1, only one request per connection is allowed at a time. This leads to a phenomenon known as head-of-line blocking, where the rendering of a web page is delayed due to dependencies on resources fetched earlier in the queue.
			HTTP/2: HTTP/2 supports multiplexing, which means multiple requests and responses can be sent and received concurrently over a single TCP connection. This significantly reduces latency and speeds up page loading times, as resources can be fetched in parallel without being blocked by others.

2.Header Compression:
			HTTP/1.1: Each request and response in HTTP/1.1 includes headers containing metadata about the communication. These headers are often verbose and redundant, leading to increased overhead.
			HTTP/2: HTTP/2 introduces header compression using the HPACK algorithm, which reduces the size of headers by encoding frequently repeated headers only once and referencing them later. This results in more efficient use of network resources and improved performance.

3.Server Push:

			HTTP/1.1: In HTTP/1.1, the client must explicitly request each resource required to render a web page. This can lead to suboptimal performance, especially for resources that the server knows the client will need.
			HTTP/2: HTTP/2 introduces server push, allowing the server to preemptively push resources to the client's cache without waiting for explicit requests. This can reduce the number of round trips required to fetch resources, further improving performance.

4.Binary Protocol:
			HTTP/1.1: HTTP/1.1 is a text-based protocol, which means requests and responses are transmitted as plain text. While human-readable, this format can be inefficient for parsing and processing by machines.
			HTTP/2: HTTP/2 is a binary protocol, meaning requests and responses are serialized in binary format. This reduces overhead and simplifies parsing, resulting in faster and more efficient communication between clients and servers.

5.Backward Compatibility
			HTTP/1.1: HTTP/1.1 is widely supported by web servers and clients, making it the de facto standard for web communication. However, its limitations have become more apparent as web applications have become more complex.
			HTTP/2: HTTP/2 is designed to be backward compatible with HTTP/1.1, allowing existing web infrastructure to be upgraded gradually. Servers that support HTTP/2 can negotiate with clients to determine which protocol version to use for communication.
			
Conclusion: HTTP/2 represents a significant advancement over HTTP/1.1 in terms of performance, efficiency, and functionality. By introducing features such as multiplexing, header compression, server push, and a binary protocol.


2.Write a blog about objects and its internal representation in Javascript ?

In JavaScript, an object is a complex data type that allows you to store and organize data in key-value pairs. Objects can represent real-world entities and are used to model and manipulate information efficiently.
 

Objects and properties

The properties of an object define the characteristics of the object. You access the properties of an object with a simple dot-notation: 

objectName.propertyName 

var myCar = new Object(); myCar.make = 'Ford'; myCar.model = 'Mustang'; myCar.year = 1969; 

Properties of JavaScript objects can also be accessed or set using a bracket notation 

myCar['make'] = 'Ford'; myCar['model'] = 'Mustang'; myCar['year'] = 1969; 
 Objects can contain not only data properties but also methods, which are functions associated with the object. Let’s add a method to our `person` object:

javascript code : person.greet = function() { console.log(`Hello, I’m ${this.name}!`); };

Now, our `person` object has a `greet` method that logs a greeting.

Prototypes and Inheritance:
 JavaScript is a prototype-based language, and objects can inherit properties and methods from other objects through their prototypes. This mechanism enables the creation of hierarchical structures.
In the JS code, you can see how objects and their prototypes are linked, forming a chain of inheritance.

const parent = {
  greet() {
    console.log('Hello from the parent object!');
  }
};

const child = Object.create(parent);
child.greet(); // Output: Hello from the parent object!


3.Read about IP address, port, HTTP methods, MAC address ?

IP Address
An IP (Internet Protocol) address is a unique numerical label assigned to each device connected to a computer network that uses the Internet Protocol for communication. IP addresses serve two primary purposes: identifying the host or network interface and providing a location address.
IP addresses come in two main versions: IPv4 and IPv6. IPv4 addresses are 32-bit numerical values typically expressed in dotted-decimal notation (e.g., 192.0.2.1), while IPv6 addresses are 128-bit values expressed in hexadecimal notation (e.g., 2001:0db8:85a3:0000:0000:8a2e:0370:7334).

Port
A port is a communication endpoint used by computers to send and receive data over a network. In TCP/IP networking, ports are identified by 16-bit unsigned integers, allowing a single host to support multiple simultaneous network services. Ports are commonly associated with specific protocols or services. For example, HTTP typically uses port 80, HTTPS uses port 443, SSH uses port 22, etc.

HTTP Methods

HTTP (Hypertext Transfer Protocol) methods, also known as HTTP verbs, are actions that indicate the desired operation to be performed on a resource identified by a URI (Uniform Resource Identifier). The most common HTTP methods include:
	·	GET: Requests data from a specified resource.
	·	POST: Submits data to be processed to a specified resource.
	·	PUT: Uploads data to a specified resource, replacing any existing data.
	·	DELETE: Deletes the specified resource.
	·	PATCH: Applies partial modifications to a resource.
	·	HEAD: Requests the headers of a specified resource without transferring the actual data.
	·	OPTIONS: Requests information about the communication options available for the target resource.
These methods define the semantics of the request and the corresponding action that should be taken by the server.

MAC Address

A MAC (Media Access Control) address, also known as a hardware address or physical address, is a unique identifier assigned to each network interface controller (NIC) of a device. MAC addresses are assigned by the manufacturer and are used at the data link layer of the OSI model to facilitate communication within a local network segment.
MAC addresses are typically represented as six groups of two hexadecimal digits separated by colons or hyphens (e.g., 00:1A:2B:3C:4D:5E). Unlike IP addresses, MAC addresses are burned into the hardware of the network interface and cannot be changed.

















